So we're this is a this is a big step to show our commitment to making sure that my Emma is a place that people
want to live and
Does it
Okay, well, thank you
Item eight is public input on schedule personal appearances and the audience it wishes to address the council on the need of the remaining
Agenda items
They're being done out of nine is considered gender staff is recommending items two and through 17 for the consent agenda
Matter there's no objection all my commotion pretty bottoms 10 through 17 on consent in and a second
I'll sink in it. Roll call
Shelton
I
Wester
All right
I have a meeting letter of agreement option A with the ETC Institute to conduct a community survey on a five-room
Work for the city of Miami power. How are you tonight? Yeah, so I'm doing good
We would like to
Have ETC come in and conduct a community right survey
I'm doing sure if a five-room network is one of about the citizens of Miami
This is since could use it for internet
Cobo
phone
video services
The city could use the if we ever wanted to do smart majoring
That's smart infrastructure and we had the Tennessee Valley Association believe come down last fall and talk about everything
They do with the five-room network as far as the city
So before we you know go and actually bring somebody in to actually need to know if it's one in the community or not so
ETC will conduct the survey determine if it's wanted in the city
Did
Orphan or do you know what kind of penetration percentage they're looking for as an ideal as we understand from both
They need a 40% penetration rate to make this work financially and
And it just a reminder about what we're trying to deal with here
We've held off a little bit because we want to been willing to be able to take a look at this concept to make sure he was comfortable with it as well
And again, I want to stress that all we're doing tonight has asking your
permission to move ahead with ETC and I'll talk about them in just a moment
But because of the restrictions on REC and bold they cannot spend money in the city limits because we're an urban area in their overall
Cooperative even though they are literally at our door
That I think there are a number of people in the room right now that could probably have bold hooked up to their home
But what the concept here and we do have funds in our budget is that we would do
We would fund some of the initial work to start constructing
Once the construction takes place and bold start selling services to those new
Members then they would take that revenue and they continue to build out so the rest of the town is build out
But the estimate to the city and this is not an in substantial amount of money that over a couple of years we're estimating that this could be one million to a million twenty five
twenty five hundred twenty five thousand dollars. This is not an inexpensive amount. And then on top of that we're going to need to look at our rate structure to see what we would need to be able to have this hard type meters to be able to take up a fact on the fiber.
But one of the long-range goals of this is, for example, we continually point out that we have a number of a number of accounts that are in our rears.
We have about over a million dollars of uncollected bills that we probably will never collect.
If we can have some type of a smart fiber system, we can probably get collections much quicker.
We can even sell electricity ahead of time.
In other words, like cable where you pay an advance to set up paying a rears.
So we don't have people behind.
So eventually, even though it's going to be a very large investment, it can be something that could be very cost effective in the city.
But on top of that, what it means is that our citizens on top of having the smart meter,
they will be able to use that network to be able to have ultra-high speed internet.
And when we talk about that, we're talking about the speeds that you read about Google fiber.
This is what we're talking about.
Community of this size having something like this would be incredibly unique.
On top of that, they would provide another option for our customers for cable television.
And also another option for our customers for telephoto.
And that would be directly with bolt.
So when you're taking a look at this, even though we're talking about an $18,000 cost right now that we would have to incur,
it could potentially move my aim of very far ahead of any of our competitors.
When you think about economic development anymore, it's not property.
It's technology.
And this is an opportunity to make technology work that we've got to have that type of penetration.
If we have our customers, if our citizens say they're not interested in something like this,
then it won't work financially and we won't be able to do this.
But it's worth the effort.
It's worth making this question.
One last thing I want to point out, ETC is a company that I worked with substantially when I was in Branson.
They're based in Kansas City and their specialty is doing surveys for governmental units of their citizens.
So this is not, this is basically a firm in which they will come in.
They will do a scientific survey.
This isn't a question that you'll find on Facebook.
I mean, this is calling people on a scientific random survey asking them very specific questions
and coming up with a database.
Because if we're talking about making this type of investment with our tax and utility dollars,
we have to be very confident in where we go.
We really don't have a margin of error here.
So we think a very good scientific survey like this is something to be able to give us.
and get the gold either the assurance to move forward or the assurance to know that this is
something that wouldn't not necessarily work in Miami. Is that survey going to be
dored door? They do fires that you do the door and they do phone calls. They try to do it makes
that really get a total different. With so many cell phones, I'm trying to get my head ram,
how are you going to make phone call? I don't have a landline. So, they said they use these
enough fires and if you do not respond back to your fire, then they'll work with the city
possibly to get people's phone numbers or different routes to get phone numbers.
And this is the issue we have nationwide, we have the presidential election and they
continually talk about the polls. Those pollsters are having the same problems right now too,
because I don't have a landline either. And trying to find new ways to do that. So, again, that's why
having a company like this, they are able to overcome that. So, it won't just be anybody that
has a landline, we'll try to know what our citizens want. Well, the cost comparison is being about
the same as what we have available now. I'm internet and cables. Again, I think when it comes to
what they offer by way of cable, all that, that's going to be basically their business bond. We
were really not having anything to do with that. So, I think the hope that we have is they
will be competitive, because they will not be a unique utility. They'll have to compete with satellite,
they'll have to compete with cable one. And also satellite cable one will have to compete with both.
Correct, if I'm wrong, it didn't bolt, send out. This isn't as out by accident.
Oh, so I shouldn't have received that. I checked on that. I didn't. I didn't, but they asked for it,
my call. Don't pull me to this, they asked for a certain amount of money. So, they kind of did their own
information. So, now. Well, they shouldn't have, they sent the wrong mail or they sent it to people
within the city limits. That was intended for people outside the city. Because they can serve people outside
the city limits. You know, I kind of agree with that, I just say, this isn't. I think it's a
great plan. And I'm, I'm in boards to hearing more down the road. But, you know, $18,000
a lot of money to have a survey done. And it's unfortunate that they can't do it because we're
seedling it. And if I'm correct me from wrong, Grove, did they do this in the other area communities?
Did they, were they able to go, when they went to Grove, they could sort of grow to be a little
community. So, they, they were allowed to serve and grow, but they're not allowed to serve and
lay on them. Because I agree if they were allowed to serve and lay on them, we wouldn't be having a
conversation. And so, restrictions they haven't already seed. No one will just turn to serve, I'm going to tell
I believe it's a three-month period, three-month period.
Three-month period.
How quick does it take place when would they start?
It's not waiting for a staff as soon as it's approved as far as developing a question here.
And then the run kind of a sample on the question here just to make sure everyone understands it.
And of course we'll be working with both on the question there as well.
And this is going out to 400 households.
That's a minimum, but we're going to do a lot more than that, they say they start, they just start throwing them out.
And I'm like, I just don't know, because that's what I'm doing the same question I had.
And so that's the minimum, they said they usually get a lot more than that.
I mean, they will definitely try to get a lot more than that.
Being a zispy only, is just only company that can do this or is it comparable in price to everybody else?
It's a really comparable price to what I've experienced.
Now, when we were working on this, I contacted them because this is a company that I,
I know they're just in Kansas City, they do excellent work.
Other companies we would have to that.
And this is very, very specialized.
So in order to move this along, I reached out to people that I've already worked with and my other jobs,
knowing that they can produce what we need.
And their pricing is very similar.
What I experienced in other communities.
I mean, with this, these types of questions are we building the question you said,
we're going to kind of develop.
Yes, correct.
I mean, is it something that we could do it to find out in our own, through our own utilities?
We don't we have better access to the people that are.
The difficulty you have is, if you're not, if you're not doing a true scientific survey,
where you have that type of sampling, your results could be skewed.
As I said, we could put a question here on Facebook and if somebody just happens to see it,
but it's not anything that you would really be able to base a business decision on.
This is, this is a business decision that we're looking at.
And we really want to make sure that we have kind of the background and everything in both wants to have that kind of background to make sure.
It's it's, it's what companies would do before they launch a product.
Questions in my utility bills that go out to the customers and they answer them.
And when they pay their bill, they turn that in.
If they're lying or telling the truth, what is there a different thing?
Whenever somebody calls them on the phone,
while they're eating and they're running through the question well, I guess I guess it's a lot of money.
It's just that you have a random sample and again, it's that that scientific sampling that you have rather than just somebody that happens to notice it on their bill.
Well, the surveys go out to households as well as businesses.
Yes, sir.
Currently servicing some businesses.
I believe so, yes.
But we will send that out to businesses.
I guess my question would be.
and they surveyed, are they going to be asking the question, if it's in their pricing,
because there's no pricing in there and just on a general basis, yeah, I'm interested in it,
but if it's something I can't afford, no, I'm not going to do it.
I mean, they were said, it's a matter of saying they were said to reigns.
Would you be interested for a one-week service for around this range?
Would you be interested if you had a specific amount of that?
I'll say it.
But I'm that also gives you the reason why you would want to have that random survey,
where you're having somebody asking those questions and exploring,
rather than just somebody with a piece of paper.
Right, you want to keep drawing us.
Sorry, man.
No, I'm just less than that.
I'm sure a bolt is done this before, right?
This type of survey, I honestly do not know, because this is a very unique situation.
With REC developing bolt, they are just very in the grand Lake area and they are coming up here.
This, when we started working with bolt, they said, this is unique,
because my Emma is a community they would love to serve in,
but because of their financial restrictions, they cannot come in to town.
So, in our discussions with them, we kind of crafted this idea on how they could come in and serve the city of my Emma.
But in order to do that, we were talking about, let's have a survey,
because while we're talking about 18,000, being a lot of money, and it is,
if we feel comfortable enough, move, we're going to be spending far more than that.
And we want to be absolutely assured that we're spending that money properly.
We'd hate to not have a survey where everybody says, yes, we're going to do it,
and then get started and then find out nobody does.
I just think, we've been talking about this for a year and a year.
In every conversation, everybody up here is doing that bolt was going to pay for the survey now.
Because they have it made sense for them to come here.
Emma trouble is they can't spend it on the survey just for the same reason.
They can't come into the community using their funds.
Is 18,000 is budgeted?
Yes.
In fact, in our budget for this project, we have a half a million dollars.
You've mentioned cable one a couple of times in regards to them and satellite.
Has we heard from cable one?
Actually, cable one did approach us, because they've probably seen some advertising,
so we're there talking about a gigabit service.
So we actually sat down with cable one and we basically went over this concept and said,
can you match it?
And after a few weeks, they came back and said, no, we really can't do that.
See the difference here with cable one, if you see a gigabit service with cable one,
and I'm looking at Mikey because he probably can explain it a little better.
It's a gigabyte up to you, but not a gigabyte out.
Which here we're talking about a gigabit and a gigabit,
which is really the type that takes advantage of the fiber and really gives you the type of service that is just...
you know, ultra high speed.
That's exactly correct. It's the up and down.
Yeah.
And again, cable one finally.
Because we told cable one of you could do it great.
And we'd be just as interested in working with you,
but they basically took a pass.
And so, Mikey, why do you think that is?
I had the impression that they were building,
I don't know if the problem with term is ahead,
or whatever it is.
And then fiber of two my am I, and that their role was to build out.
It's their coax backbone in the neighborhoods.
Right.
And so they're not planning to replace that.
Not it.
No.
Did you hear a word?
Did you hear any of that in our meetings?
No.
There's still a couple of water.
Fiber on the pole from the pole to the house.
I don't know what that concept.
Okay.
But whatever.
And they said they couldn't match.
So they could not match this.
It's unfortunate.
I think it'd be great to get in here.
I don't know what that means.
And I just have to ask these questions because it is a lot of money.
But I understand it is a lot of money in the long run.
So, you know, I want to true serve a guy sometimes.
Yeah.
I know it's like whenever somebody tries to call me.
And then I, whenever.
Yeah.
Even though.
Whatever.
I, you know.
So if this does go through, I bang for everybody
to answer it all this.
Yeah.
And that's what's there for it.
So.
If our citizens don't want to serve us and we can't proceed.
And we've got to have a good estimation if this is going to happen.
So we're looking at the first and next year.
Probably so.
Yes.
Which is halfway through our fiscal year.
Yeah.
In more questions.
I agree that it has to be a professional survey.
Because there's too much money at risk.
I'm very, very busy putting it risk.
And this is such a unique situation.
I mean, I don't know of any other communities that have ever done anything like this.
So we really got to proceed cautiously.
I might have to.
There's no.
First.
Gosh.
I'll make a motion to a burn.
Okay.
You have a motion to the other second.
All second.
Roll call.
Johnson.
Aye.
Forster.
Lewis.
Aye.
Western.
Shows.
Aye.
And the first call needs to be to Dr. Gilbert.
Thank you.
Okay.
So.
Item number.
19 new business and new business.
Item 20 is announcements in the announcements?
I just didn't want, I'd like to congratulate Judy and Ronnie and Glenda here before
along.
She's worried about two more months.
So what you got?
To give her a tag.
You know, the people is on their agenda night, Christy Travis and if I'm missing somebody, I think
we have a great city crew and we're going to be mass good and good employees.
I agree.
Okay, city manager communications need?
Just some very quick ones.
We've been working with the, with DD and the women's shelter and we're going to have a kind
of a small parade and unveiling a firm hallway on October 19 starting at noon and just kind
of a nice way.
I've been very proud of the street department, I don't think we have anybody here representing
that department right now but they've done a really great job on the bracket so we'll
be holding that sign and that's going to be taking place so I just want everybody to be aware
of that.
Also we'll see a lot of people around here wearing pink, breast cancer awareness and I'm not
only a fire department doing their usual t-shirts but also our sanitation department.
Solid waste is doing paint t-shirts as well and they're doing their share.
We have a chance to take Neil through the animal shelter over this week and right now we're
just taking care of the punch list and a few other corrections that need to be done and
also we're assembling the pens that will be in the shelter but it's very impressive facility
and looking forward to getting that taken care of.
So I started on the, yes they have time for any time frame.
Time frame I think as soon as we can, as the furniture and stuff all come into I think the furniture
has been delivered yet.
Okay, so anyway that's working quickly so very soon we need to have kind of ribbon cutting and
recognition what's taking place there.
We also have the plaque that's going to be going up but also signage we're working on with
Kobe Allen so we'll have that taken care of too.
I know that Tyler wanted everybody to know that we've got the Walmart switch in so he's going
to get ready to start doing that work so happy to have that done and also 66 landing as underway.
Their contractors are in town and things closed off and they're getting ready we're picking
out parking spaces the other day and that project is getting underway.
So a lot of good things have.
That's so exciting I guess I'll say in there you know the signs that project they're going to
in field 20 is it's 20 at 21 18 18 house houses within the half mile of that project that's
just awesome.
You know you construction we've had in my Emma in decades so using years and years and years so
that's very exciting.
Anything else?
We do not need an executive session tonight so I'm 23 as a drummer.
Brian, did you?
All right.
Most of them are the chair.
And a second. Second. Roll fall.
Is it a register?
Hi.
Question?
Is it a sign?
No.
Hi.
Thank you, everyone.
Good to be able to talk with all the members.